# Wilson Yan

## Google Scholar wilson1.yan@berkeley.edu wilsonyan.com

My goal is to equip artificial intelligence (AI) with a deep understanding of the physical world. As such, my research focuses on designing scalable video models that generate long and complex video, thereby teaching them an understanding of 3D geometry, physics, and the physical properties of objects. Tackling this challenge, I have been fortunate to publish several papers in top venues, presenting novel video models and their applications to decision making agents.

#### **Education**

## **University of California, Berkeley**

2020 - Now

PhD Computer Science Advisor: *Pieter Abbeel* GPA: 3.89 / 4.00

### University of California, Berkeley

2016 - 2020

Bachelor of the Arts in Computer Science and Applied Math

GPA: 3.97 / 4.00

#### **Employment**

### Google DeepMind, GenAl

06/2023 - 10/2023

Senior Research Scientist

Working on large-scale world models for decision making.

Meta, GenAl 06/2023 - 10/2023

#### PhD Research Intern

Trained large-scale video generation models and implemented image/video editing methods. Explored motion representations (optical flow, motion vectors) as model input and for data filtering. Released a state-of-the-art algorithm for general video editing (see papers).

**Perplexity AI** 10/2022 – 03/2023

#### PhD Research Intern

Internship at a fast-growing AI startup.

Developed retrieval and reranking mechanisms to improve generation quality.

Implemented data filtering techniques to construct high-quality finetuning datasets.

Trained and deployed the first in-house LLM to replace OpenAI API inference.

## Robot Learning Lab (BAIR)

01/2018 - 03/2020

## Research Assistant

Conducted several research projects across reinforcement learning, robotics, and generative modeling.

**Papers** 

World Model on Million-Length Video And Language With RingAttention

Preprint

H Liu, <u>W Yan</u>, M Zaharia, P Abbeel

Motion-Conditioned Image Animation for Video Editing

**Preprint** 

W Yan, A Brown, P Abbeel, R Girdhar, S Azadi

Video Prediction Models as Rewards for Reinforcement Learning

NeurIPS 2023

A Escontrela\*, A Adeniji\*, <u>W Yan\*</u>, A Jain, XB Peng, K Goldberg Y Lee, D Hafner, P Abbeel

Language Quantized AutoEncoders: Towards Unsupervised

NeurlPS 2023

Text-Image Alignment

H Liu, <u>W Yan</u>,, P Abbeel

Temporally Consistent Video Transformer for Long-Term Video Prediction

**ICML 2023** 

<u>W Yan</u>, D Hafner, S James, P Abbeel

Patch-based Object-centric Transformers for Efficient Video Generation

**Preprint** 

W Yan, R Okumura, S James, P Abbeel

VideoGPT: Video Generation Using VQ-VAE and Transformers

Preprint

W Yan\*, Y Zhang\*, P Abbeel, A Srinivas

Learning Predictive Representations for Deformable Objects Using

**CoRL 2020** 

**Contrastive Estimation** 

W Yan, A Vangipuram, P Abbeel, L Pinto

**Learning to Manipulate Deformable Objects without Demonstrations** 

**RSS 2020** 

Y Wu\*, <u>W Yan\*</u>, T Kurutach, L Pinto, P Abbeel

Software

Large World Model Link

6900 stars

Open-source 1 million context-length multimodal foundation model.

VideoGPT Link

600 stars

Video Generation with VQ-VAE and Transformers.

DeepUL <u>Link</u>

600 stars

Course homework and demos for Deep Unsupervised Learning.

**Teaching** 

**Introduction to Artificial Intelligence** CS 188

Fall 2018, Spring 2019, Fall 2019

TA for Fall 2019 and Spring 2019. Head TA for Fall 2019 (Managing a course of over 400 students).

**Deep Unsupervised Learning** CS 294-158

Spring 2020, Spring 2024

Co-Head TA for Spring 2020 and Lecturer for Spring 2024 over a graduate course with 100 PhD students.

Reviewing

Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)

2022, 2023

International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)

2023